Finding Aid for Dalgleish family business records, 1929-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dalgleish family business records 1929-2013 1950s-1990s
Dalgleish family.
2013077 Aa 2
Records of car dealerships owned by the Dalgleish family of Detroit, Michigan. Advertising and customer service material, photographs, selected business records, and artifacts. The collection is of special interest to researchers of Detroit business community and to the U.S. automobile industry and trade historians. Collection is especially rich with material related to auto advertising, particularly, the Cadillac.
1.3 linear feet in 2 boxes including oversize
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Charles Dalgleish, Jr. (Donor no. 10966 ) in July 2013.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Dalgleish family owned auto dealership businesses in Detroit for 70 years. Charles H. Dalgleish Sr., the only son of Mr. and Mrs. K. M. Dalgleish, came to Detroit from Kenmore, Ontario in 1922. He first worked for the Miller Judd Company, a Nash auto distributor. In 1929, one month before the stock market crashed, Dalgleish opened his first business, Charlie's Nash Service Garage, located at 4940 Joy Rd. in Detroit. In 1933 Dalgleish became a Nash franchise and changed its name to Charlie's Nash Sales & Service, or Charlie's Nash. Charlie's Nash eventually became the largest Nash dealership in the world, and was the oldest Nash dealership in Detroit, one of the two oldest in Michigan.
In 1940 Charles Dalgleish became Director of Detroit Auto Dealers Association (DADA) and was elected DADA president in 1950. In 1952 he became Director of the National Automobile Dealers Association (NADA) and served on NADA Business Management Committee in 1954.
Charles Dalgleish's two sons, Charles Jr. and Douglas Sr., both graduates of the University of Michigan, also joined the family business. Charles Jr. started in 1947 after serving in the military. Douglas Sr. followed his brother in 1950. The brothers worked together between 1950 and 1954.
In 1954 Charles Sr. purchased an Oldsmobile-Cadillac franchise. On January 1, 1955 Charlie's Oldsmobile Cadillac, Inc. (subsidiary of Charlie's Nash, Inc.), was merged with Charlie's Nash, Inc., and the corporate name of Charlie's Nash, Inc. was changed to Charlie's Oldsmobile Cadillac. Charles Dalgleish Jr. moved with the Cadillac franchise to Grand River Avenue, while Douglas Sr. stayed with Charlie's Oldsmobile. In 1964 Charles Jr. moved his business to the site of the first Cadillac plant designed by Albert Kahn in the 1920s on Cass Avenue in Detroit's New Amsterdam Historic district. In 1969 Douglas Sr. and several other auto dealers came with an idea of Detroit Auto Show dealers-only charity previews, and was instrumental in organizing Friday evening previews that raised millions of dollars for charities. The collection includes a photograph taken during the 1969 preview show depicting Douglas Jr. and the President of General Motors Ed Cole (the photograph can be found in the Photographs folder within the Dalgleish Dealerships series). After Douglas Sr. closed his business in the 1970s, he came to work with his brother. Charles Dalgleish Jr. served as the Dalgleish Cadillac President and Treasurer while Douglas Dalgleish Sr. served as the company's Vice President and Secretary. In 1983 Dalgleish became a Peugeot dealer.
During over 70 years of Dalgleish Cadillac Oldsmobile existence, four Dalgleish generations worked in the family business. Mary Alice O'Brien-Mecke's 2001 Automotive News article listed all Dalgleish family members who were employed by the business. Charles and Douglas' sister Muriel Schaffer served as a social events representative. Douglas Sr.' three sons served in different capacities: Douglas Jr. was general manager and sales manager for Cadillac; Timothy worked as sales manager for Oldsmobiles; Keith was used-car manager and computer specialist. Douglas Sr.' daughter-in-law Dona Dalgleish worked in the billing department, her son Drew worked summers and holidays in the parts department, among other duties. Douglas Jr.' two sons also were part of the family business: Christopher worked in the parts department; Justin, at the time a student at Albion College, worked summers and holidays on miscellaneous jobs. (Mary Alice O'Brien-Mecke Automotive News: February 5, 2001). Justin eventually became Dalgleish Finance and Insurance Manager.
Dalgleish Cadillac closed in 2010. It was the last dealership to sell Cadillacs in Detroit. In early 2010 the Dalgleish dealership building was purchased by Wayne State University to make it--after extensive renovation--the University's Multidisciplinary Biomedical Research Building.
The Dalgleish Cadillac Oldsmobile collection encompasses the history of the family-owned business from the 1930s through the 2010s. Depending on the time period and particular marketing campaigns, Dalgleish dealership appeared in advertising material and customer service mailings as Charles Dalgleish Cadillac, Dalgleish Cadillac, Dalgleish Oldsmobile Cadillac, and Dalgleish Peugeot. Organization of material follows the company's history, transformations, and changes of name. The collection is organized into five series: Charles H. Dalgleish, Sr., Charlie's Nash, Inc., Charlie's Oldsmobile, Dalgleish Dealerships, and Advertising Material.
Subjects:
Dalgleish family.; Dalgleish, Charles.; Automobile dealers--Michigan--Detroit.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan--Detroit.; Cadillac automobile.; Dalgleish Cadillac.; Family-owned business enterprises--Michigan--Detroit.; Nash automobiles.; Oldsmobile automobile.; Peugeot automobile.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Automobile dealerships--Michigan--Detroit.; Automobiles.
Contributors:
Dalgleish, Charles.
Genre Terms:
Advertisements.; Lapel pins.; Photographs.
- Charles H. Dalgleish, Sr. 1948-1983
  The Charles H. Dalgleish, Sr. series (0.2 linear feet, 1948-1983) documents activities of the Dalgleish family patriarch from the time when his eldest son Charles Jr. joined the business, through Charles Sr. 50th anniversary in business (1973), and later years. Material reflects on Charles Sr. personal and professional qualities as a successful businessman and business leader and includes correspondence, newspaper clippings, drafts of speeches, photographs, and a collection of name badges from conferences and meetings.
  - 50th anniversary in business 1973 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1948-1973 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Detroit Auto Dealers Association 1950, 1982 (Box 1)
  - National Automobile Dealers Association 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings 1950-1983 (Box 1)
  - Photographs 1950s-1970s, undated (Box 1)
  - Charles H. Dalgleish, Sr. badges (Box 1)
- Charlie's Nash 1928-1953
  The Charlie's Nash, Inc. series (0.3 linear feet, 1928-1953) includes business correspondence and agreements, customer care correspondence with description of services provided by Charlie's Nash dealership and prices. Photographs include portraits of the Dalgleish family, Nash employees, exterior and interior views of the building, and a group of photographs with George Mason, President of Nash Kelvinator. Also included a pencil with Charlie's Nash dealership name and address, most likely used for advertising purposes.
  - Business records 1943-1953 (Box 1)
  - Customer care 1930-1932, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs 1928-1953, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Charlie's Nash pencil, approximately 1951 (Box 1)
- Charlie's Oldsmobile 1954-1967
  The Charlie's Oldsmobile series (0.1 linear feet, 1954-1967) contains business records(agreements and correspondence), customer care mailings to Cadillac owners advertising services, and photographs depicting Charles Dalgleish Jr. with colleagues. Also included a pencil with Charlie's Oldsmobile dealership name and address, most likely used for advertising purposes.
  - Business records 1955, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Customer service 1960s (Box 1)
  - Photographs 1954-1967 (Box 1)
  - Charlie's Oldsmobile pencil (Box 1)
- Dalgleish Dealerships 1963-2013
  The Dalgleish Dealerships series (0.3 linear feet, 1964-2013) includes materials related to businesses with "Dalgleish" as part of business name: Charles Dalgleish Cadillac, Dalgleish Cadillac, Dalgleish Peugeot, etc. Here are found business records (agreements and correspondence), customer care correspondence, miscellaneous clippings, photographs and photo negatives depicting exterior of the Dalgleish dealership buildings, advertising signs, group photographs of Dalgleish family members and dealership employees. The series includes a framed collection of commemorative Cadillac pins. Also included is a 1976 field-work paper Folklore of the Parts and Service Departments of Dalgleish Cadillac by Diane Milatovich. The paper contains linguistic analyses and Dalgleish employees' biographical sketches.
  - Business records 1964-1969, 1986-1998 with gaps
    - 1960s (Box 1)
    - 1970s (Box 1)
    - 1980s (Box 1)
    - 2000s undated (Box 1)
  - Cadillac pins 1902-2000 (Box 1)
  - Customer service 1970s-2000s, undated (Box 1)
  - Folklore of the Parts and Service Departments of Dalgleish Cadillac by Diane Milatovich, 1976 (Box 1)
  - International dinner mats (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1980-2013 with gaps (Box 1)
  - Visual materials
    - Photographs 1960s-2000s (Box 1)
    - Photographs, outsize (Box 2)
    - Negatives (Box 1)
- Advertising material 1951-2008
  The Advertising Material series (0.4 linear feet, 1951-2008) is the largest series in the collection and contains examples of newspaper ads, flyers, invitations to special events and presentations, postcards, calendars, artwork, atlases and guides published by the Dalgleish business.
  - Cadillac 1956-2000s with gaps
    - Cards and invitations (Box 1)
    - Letters to customers (Box 1)
  - Charlie's Nash 1951-1954 (Box 1)
  - Dalgleish sales force 1970s-2000s (Box 1)
  - General 1960s-1990s, undated
    - Flyers and mailings (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - New cars, late 1960s-2008, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Newspaper ads, general 1966-1969 (Box 1)
  - Oldsmobile 1955-1958 (Box 1)
  - Other Michigan businesses
    - Auto dealers 1960s-2000s (Box 1)
    - Cadillac Motor Car Division 1967, 1975, 1996 (Box 1)
    - General Motors 2000s (Box 1)
    - Other (Box 1)
  - Peugeot 1983-1987 (Box 1)
  - Publications and printed material
    - Atlases and guides (Box 1)
    - Calendars 1974, 2004, 2007-2008 (Box 2)
    - Color-etch prints
      - Lionel Barrymore, 2 volumes (Box 2)
      - Robert Kern, 2 volumes (Box 2)
      - William R. McCarroll (Box 2)
      - Fred Sweney (Box 2)
    - Cranbrook Academy of Art flyer (Box 2)
    - Dalgleish--for Four Generations by Mary Alice O'Brien-Mecke Automotive News: February 5, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Postcards and greeting cards (Box 1)